A Guide to the Executive Office Records of Virginia Governor George F. Allen, 1993-1998
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive Office Records of Virginia Governor George F. Allen, 1993-1998
The Library of Virginia
35861 and 36192
5.65 cu. ft. (7 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1994-1998: Allen)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Georgia Root, Governor's Office, State Capitol, Richmond, Virginia, 19 June 1998.
Biographical/Historical Information
George Felix Allen was born March 8, 1952 in Whittier, California to famed NFL football coach George H. Allen and his wife Henrietta (Lumbroso) Allen. He graduated from the University of Virginia in 1971 and the University of Virginia School of Law in 1977. Allen served in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1982-1991 and served a short term in the U.S. House of Delegates in the early 1990s. In November 1993, Allen beat Attorney General Mary Sue Terry to become Governor. Governor Allen served until January 1998 and was succeeded by Governor James S. Gilmore. Governor Allen has been married to Susan (Brown) Allen since 1986 and they have three children, Forrest, Tyler, and Brooke. The family resides in Mount Vernon, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Contains files related to the activities of Governor George F. Allen's Executive Office maintained by Governor Allen's Chief of Staff, Jay Timmons. Many of the files pertain to cabinet secretariats, agencies, offices, and commissions. Also included are reports, correspondence, and subject files related to specific administration issues and events, as well as photographs of the Executive Office area and many of Governor Allen's staff members.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Secretariat and Agency Files
Series II. Subject Files
Series III. Photographs and Plans
Contents List
- Series I. Secretariat and Agency Files, 1994-1997., Extent: 3.3 cu. ft. (Box 1-4)
  Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence related to the activities of the secretariats, certain agencies, commissions, and offices. The files also contain material that documents specific issues such as the Business-Education Partnership Program, the Virginia Prepaid Education Program, welfare reform, and the Clean Air Act. Also included are files created by Chief of Staff, Jay Timmons that contain correspondence, memoranda, speeches, and decision briefs. All secretariat and agency files are part of accession 35861.
  Arranged by secretariat, agency, or office.
  - Secretary of Administration.
    - General Correspondence, 1994-1997. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 900 E. Main Street, 1994. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Combined Virginia Campaign, 1994. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Workforce Transition Act, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Commonwealth Competition Council, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Employee Relations Counselors, Dept. of, 1995-1997. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General Services, Dept. of, 1995-1997. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General Services, Dept. of, (Collocation Plan for the Governor's Cabinet), 1994. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Information Management, Council on, 1995-1996. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Information Technology, Dept. of, 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Local Government, Commission on, 1997. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Personnel and Training, Dept. of, 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Secretary of Commerce and Trade.
    - General Correspondence, 1994-1995. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Devolution, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Dept. of, 1994-1997. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Base Retention/Defense Adjustment Commission, 1994-1997. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Housing and Community Development, Dept. of, 1994-1997. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Mines, Minerals and Energy, Dept. of, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Minority Business Enterprises, Dept. of, 1994-1995. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Professional and Occupational Regulation, Dept. of, 1994-1995. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Virginia Employment Commission, 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Secretary of Education.
    - General Correspondence, 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Business-Education Partnership Program, Virginia, 1994. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Business-Education Partnership Program, Virginia, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Business-Education Partnership Program, Virginia, 1996. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Business-Education Partnership Program, Virginia, 1997. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Business-Education Partnership Program, Virginia, 1997-1998. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Higher Education, 1994-1997. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Higher Education (Old Dominion University), 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Higher Education (George Mason University), 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Elementary and Secondary Public Education Costs, 1997. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Privitization of Teaching Hospitals, 1995-1996. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Education, Dept. of, 1994-1997. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Education, Dept. of (Special Education), 1994. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Education, Dept. of (Standards of Learning/Accreditation), 1995-1997. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Higher Education, Council of, 1994-1997. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Library of Virginia, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, 1996. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Virginia Education Loan Authority, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Secretary of Finance.
    - General Correspondence, 1994. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - General Correspondence, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - General Correspondence, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - General Correspondence, 1996. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1997. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Revenue Reports, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Revenue Reports, 1995. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Revenue Reports, 1996. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Revenue Reports, 1997. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Revenue Forecasts, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Smithsonian, 1995-1996. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Prepaid Education Program, 1996. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 1994-1996. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Planning and Budget, Dept. of, 1994-1996. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - State Internal Auditor, Dept. of, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Taxation, Dept. of, 1994-1997. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Treasury, Dept. of the, 1994-1995. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Secretary of Health and Human Resources.
    - General Correspondence, 1994-1995. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - General Correspondence, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Welfare Reform, 1995-1997. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Aging, Dept. for the, 1995. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Citizen Impowerment, Governor's Commission on, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Health, Dept. of, 1994; 1997. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Medical Assistance Services, Dept. of, 1995. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Dept. of, 1995-1997. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Social Services, Dept. of, 1995-1997. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Secretary of Natural Resources.
    - General Correspondence, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - General Correspondence, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - General Correspondence, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - General Correspondence, 1995-1996. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - General Correspondence, 1997. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Chesapeake Bay, 1994-1996. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Secretary of Public Safety.
    - General Correspondence, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - General Correspondence, 1995-1997. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Alcoholic Beverage Control, Dept. of, 1994-1997. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Emergency Services, Dept. of, 1994-1995. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Emergency Services, Dept. of, (Blizzard), 1996. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Juvenile Justice, Dept. of, 1996. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Military Affairs, Dept. of, 1994-1995. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - State Police, Dept. of, 1994-1997. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Secretary of Transportation.
    - General Correspondence, 1994 February-June. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1994 July-November. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, 1995 January-May. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, 1995 June-November. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 1996 February-October. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, 1996 November. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, 1997. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Aviation, Dept. of, 1994-1996. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of, 1996. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of, 1997. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of, 1994-1997. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Transportation, Dept. of, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Transportation, Dept. of, 1995. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Transportation, Dept. of, 1996. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Transportation, Dept. of, 1997. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Port Authority, 1997-1997. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Secretary of the Commonwealth.
    - General Correspondence, 1994-1996. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Conflict of Interest, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Lottery Department.
    - General Correspondence, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - General Correspondence, 1995. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - General Correspondence, 1996. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - General Correspondence, 1997. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Virginia Liaison Office.
    - General Correspondence, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - General Correspondence, 1995. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - General Correspondence, 1996-1997. (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Clean Air Act Policy, 1995. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission.
    - Correspondence and Reports, 1994-1997. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Commissions.
    - General, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Government Reform, Governor's Commission on, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Government Reform, Governor's Commission on, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - State and Local Government Responsibility and Taxing Authortiy, Commission on, 1997. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Chief of Staff.
    - Correspondence, 1994-1997. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Decision Briefs, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Decision Briefs, 1995 January-May. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Decision Briefs, 1995 June-September. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Decision Briefs, 1995 October-December. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Decision Briefs, 1996 January-March. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Decision Briefs, 1996 April-May. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Decision Briefs, 1996 Dune-December. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Decision Briefs, 1997 January-July. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Decision Briefs, 1997 August. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Decision Briefs, 1997 September-December. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Memoranda, 1994-1997. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Speeches, 1994-1997. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1993-1998., Extent: 2.2 cu. ft. (Box 4-7)
  Contains files pertaining to a variety of committees, organizations, issues, and events. Included are folders devoted to Governor Allen's State of the Commonwealth addresses, the Governor's Commission on Parole Abolition and Sentencing Reform, Medicaid, pfiesteria, and legislative sessions. Two large binders containing reports and other materal detailing Governor Allen's accomplishments in office are also included. All subject files are part of accession 35861, except for the final report of full-time employment levels, which is part of accession 36192.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Accomplishments of Governor George Allen: "Promises Made, Promises Kept," (Book 1), 1994-1998. (Box 5)
  - Accomplishments of Governor George Allen: "Promises Made, Promises Kept," (Book 2), 1994-1998. (Box 5)
  - Agency Leadership Workshop, 1996. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Agency Leadership Workshop, 1997. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Appalachian Regional Commission, 1994-1997. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Appointments, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Asian Trade Mission, 1996. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Auto Policy, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Baseball: Joint Subcommittee Studying Financing Options for a Baseball Stadium in Virginia, 1996-1997. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Creche at the State Capitol, 1995. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Downsizing, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Fair Labor Standards Act, 1996. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Federal Retiree Settlement, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Federal Retiree Settlement, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Federal Retiree Settlement, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Federalism Summit, 1995. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Flying of the State and National Flag, 1994-1997. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - FOIA Requests, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Full-Time Equivalent Employment Levels, Final Report, 1993-1997. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - General Obligation Bond Projects, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Goals 2000, 1996. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Holidays, 1995-1997. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Judicial Retirement System, undated. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Lag Pay, 1996. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Lake Gaston Pipeline, 1995. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Legislative Coordination, 1995-1996. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Legislative Session, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Legislative Session, 1996. (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Lego, 1993. (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Mansion, 1994-1995. (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Medicaid, 1995. (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Medicaid, 1995-1996. (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Medicaid Briefing Book, 1995. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Motor Voter, 1995-1996. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - National Governors' Association, 1994; 1997. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - National Governors' Association Education Summit, 1996. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Parole Abolition and Sentencing Reform, Governor's Commission on, 1994. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Pay for State Employees, 1996. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Personnel Policies, 1994. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Pfiesteria, 1997. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Pfiesteria, 1997. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Pfiesteria, 1997. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Pfiesteria, 1997. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Pfiesteria, 1997. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Pfiesteria, 1997. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Portrait of the Governor, 1996-1997. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Prisoner Work Programs, 1995. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Smoking Policies, 1994. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - South Africa Trade Mission, 1994. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - State/Federal Issues, 1994. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - State Governments, Council on, 1995. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - State of the Commonwealth Address, 1995. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - State of the Commonwealth Address, 1997. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Thatcher Visit, 1995. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Business Higher Education Council, 1995. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Governmental Employees Association, 1994; 1997. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Municipal League, 1995. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Washington Airports Task Force, 1994. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Series III. Photographs and Plans, 1994-1998., Extent: .15 cu. ft. (Box 7)
  Contains photographs of the executive office, some of Governor Allen's staff members including Chief of Staff, Jay Timmons, Press Secretary, Ken Stroupe, and Rick Olson, Director of Scheduling and Logistics. Also included is one folder containing floor plan drawings for the executive office area. All photographs and plans are part of accession 36192.
  Photographs are arranged by the office number printed on the back of each photograph.
  - Drawings and Plans (Executive Office), 1994-1998. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Photographs: Office Number 1 (Governor's Office), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Photographs: Office Number 2 (Assistant, Mary Barham Nardo), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Photographs: Office Number 3 (Chief of Staff, Jay Timmons), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 14-15)
  - Photographs: Office Number 4 (Conference Room), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Photographs: Office Number 5 (Reception), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
  - Photographs: Office Number 6, 1997. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Photographs: Office Number 7 (Press Secretary, Ken Stroupe), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Photographs: Office Number 8 (Press Office), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - Photographs: Office Number 9 (Speechwriter, Paul Nardo), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Photographs: Office Number 10 (Policy Office), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Photographs: Office Number 11 (Counselor and Policy Director, mark Christie), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
  - Photographs: Office Number 12, 1997. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Photographs: Office Number 13 (Joyce Walton), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Photographs: Office Number 14 (Director of Scheduling and Logistics, Rick Olson), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Photographs: Office Number 15 (Scheduling Office), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Photographs: Office Number 17 (Deputy Chief of Staff, Robert Barratta), 1997. (Box 7, Folder 18)